software engineering radio episode 64
architecture and business with Luo man
[Music]
welcome listeners to new episode of
software engineering radio in this
episode we are going to talk to Luke
Holman about or actually how do you
pronounce this in common Holman okay
because it is also more or less you
could pronounce it German well I told my
ancestry is German yeah okay and we're
going to talk about let's say the
non-technical aspects of software
architecture how to build products how
to integrate technical architectural
stuff with business concerns before we
do that I briefly want to thank the
organizers of the olp 2007 conference
because they've been giving us a room
where we can actually record this stuff
so thanks welcome later from 6th accom
very good so we can do a professionally
sounding recording here and so before we
get into the topic look I think it's
it's a good time to introduce yourself a
little bit what you do what your kind of
background is and why you're here today
thank you
hi everyone well my background is kind
of interesting I started working at EDS
and the big systems integrator and I
spent 10 years at EDS and I my first job
was pulling cable underneath raised
floor so no programming and just running
around and cabling and then over time I
did a variety of things for EDS
programming and management and I
eventually became a vice president of
engineering at a subsidiary and I moved
up the ranks if you will in management
to try and build better products for
people and then I joined a company
called object space which was a
object-oriented training and consulting
firm in Dallas Texas and lots of fun
people have come out of object-based
graham glass craig lahrman work that
object base so lots of people worked at
object space creative place create a
very creative place I ran the training
division and taught lots of C++ and
small talk and Opie and Oh a and B and
then from there I did some more products
I moved to Silicon Valley where many
products are created so I started moving
more and more under products and I
started becoming just increasingly
convinced that the business issues
of a product company in software are
deeply intertwined with the technical
issues and the architectural issues and
in fact this notion that you can kind of
separate the architecture and separate
the technical concerns became
increasingly increasingly misleading to
me and and not accurate to my experience
so I did some products and did a variety
of things and eventually I decided to
become a consultant to see if I could
move the industry forward by helping
developers both talk and work with them
with the product team and also by
helping the product people understand
technical concerns trying to bridge that
gap that it naturally exists but but if
it if the gap is too big you get
problems and if the gap is too small you
get problems and there's there's a
reason that there's a gap but we want to
have an ability to work with the other
team if you will yeah so then one of
maybe the first important distinctions
or statements is that we're specifically
talking about about product development
and not necessarily about the typical
you know IT project that's correct and
in fact my my good friend Martin Fowler
my book is I enjoy being in his series
you know but I remember when Martin and
I were talking about it and I and Martin
said I'd like to publish your book and I
said well you know it's a product
centric book and and it doesn't meet
every kind of development especially the
the vast and very important part of IT
and Martin read the book he said no I
think it I think it's really important
for IT people to also understand that
the work that they do an IT does need to
support the business it may not be as
direct as a product but but they still
have a role in supporting the business
and I think Martin's right yeah oh and
also I think it is sometimes a good a
good idea to to view a project as
delivering products that's right that
gives you a different perspective on you
know release management and these kinds
of things that's right that's right and
Martin said the same thing he's like
look you know you know the the same
disciplines and the same activities of
putting version numbers for a product
are just as important for putting
version numbers in IT because you have
to know what you've given and also the
whole notion of customers right I guess
because IP people have customers too so
there are a very small number of
things that I talked about that don't
quite relate to the IT side but most of
the things that I talk about do and most
of the things I care about the IT people
care about - okay so then let's talk
about it it's the basis for all that is
obviously software architecture right
and we've had discussions about
technical aspects of software
architecture all over the place so we're
not going to repeat that in very much
detail but so you said that you can't
easily distinguish the technicals of the
architecture from like the product
development product roadmap product
features so can you give us a little bit
of an overview why this why this goes
together and how well you know where are
the joint points yeah so the easiest
place to find the joint points is to
look at the way a company makes money
and what you find is as you examine the
ways companies make money you find that
the architectures of the technical team
to support the way the company makes
money become very different I'll give
you a concrete example yeah let's say
that you're an enterprise software and
you are going to license your software
on an annual license this is a very
common choice and it's a very good
choice and it makes sense the
architecture for managing that license
is very different from a company who
says well I'm gonna license my software
using concurrent users or named users
because in one architecture you're
tracking time and a different
architecture you're tracking logins and
user IDs and let's further distinguish
it let's say that the company was
managing transactions and they said our
software processes cell phone calls and
every time you make a cell phone call
we're gonna look at the attributes of a
call and then create a billing system
that goes along with it well that's
again a completely different technical
architecture to support the business
choice of how do I want to make money in
my market and and we have lots and lots
of books that talk about you know
pipelines in Mary Shaw's book and Martin
Fowler's book and these are all really
important things that we need Grady
Booch is cataloguing architecture yeah
that's cool which is really good stuff
but what I think we're still missing and
what we're trying to create our own
catalog and share through the book and
through other mechanisms is when your
business is making money a certain way
here's a set of natural requirement
that go to your architecture like if I'm
transactions I have to know the
lifecycle of the transaction I have to
have identifies I have to have ways to
audit them and and understand what the
transaction processing lifecycle is
again very very different from someone
who's looking at say named users or
concurrent users or counting CPUs like a
database does know that these are all
very important distinctions so just to
clarify or to to make sure people know
that the book we're talking about is
called beyond software architecture
architecture and so that's the context
in which we start this discussion here
and we'll put the URL obviously or the
link to the Amazon page into the show
notes ok can you give us a little bit of
like a product development primer so
what what happens if you develop a
product what are the most important
steps in doing that maybe also in
contrast to typical IT projects yes so
you know in in most projects there's
there's a great degree of commonality
right you have some idea of something
you want to do and then you have some
sequence of transformational steps to
produce working software so independent
of whether it's product development or
IT you can distinguish traditional
software responses to that by the
different methods we use like the berry
beam spiral or the waterfall or scrum or
agile so it's really a question of how
am i transforming these ideas into into
some kind of working software where
product management differs and there's
many dimensions in which it differs from
say traditional IT is that the product
management function is trying to
determine value in such a way that you
can charge for it whereas in the IT
you're still delivering software that
has value but you're not gonna price it
you're not gonna sell it you're not
going to distribute it please pay for
the development time they pay for the
development time and so so but the the
transformational sequence to me is the
same it's the what you do when the
software is done that makes all the
difference in terms of IT you install it
you train it you use it and products you
install it you have to sell it you have
to put it through channels you might
offer it directly over the internet you
might have a direct sales force all of
those complexities make products a
little
from just IT one of the especially
important things when developing a
product is that you can't update it
easily you have to have a like a road
map you have to have well-defined
versions you can't just about maybe
today with Internet is different so you
can easily you know put a patch into
what you already have but there needs to
be a more explicit plan of the different
releases and versions you have so I
think this is also maybe a difference
yeah so you touched on actually two
points one is the notion of a road map
and the other is the notion of how do I
support and service my customers in the
field let's take a road map first yeah
so one of the things that we think is a
dangerous thing is when product
marketing people and engineering people
simply just say I'm gonna have this
release on this date with these features
that's what we call a release train and
that doesn't provide very much
information to the company or the
engineers in the sense of well why is
this release important why do people
care to acquire this release why does my
customer want to install it and more
importantly software has natural
opportunities to be installed and what I
mean by that is that every market is
governed by a set of events and rhythms
yep and you can't just install software
anytime you want you just can't change
things around whenever you want so for
example if I'm coming to a conference
and I have an important presentation I
may not want to upgrade my operating
system while I'm on the plane on the way
to the conference because if something
goes wrong I can't recover from it and
similarly in business we we can't just
arbitrarily update things or change
things and so one of the things that a
good roadmap does is it moves beyond
just this release in this time frame and
it provides the the understanding that
the product team has about why will the
market care about this and why will the
market absorb this the other part about
this is that and and I talked about it
yesterday here at the obe conference in
my tutorial is that the we expect that
the product team has an understanding of
how the markets going to evolve and how
the features of the cup of the of the
product are going to improve well we
also understand that technology isn't
static
right technology's very dynamic yeah
very cool dynamic - dynamic yeah but the
point is is that one of the people who
are in my tutorial said hey how do I
communicate to my product team that I've
got to change my architecture because
something changed underneath me
you know I I'm fine with the old
database but the database vendor changed
versions and they no longer support it
so I have to change right now that
happens all the time in our industry
there has change very sometimes it feels
very unstable and so what I talk about
is a well-constructed roadmap is going
to give the technical architect an
opportunity to communicate their
understanding of how things are going to
evolve and their understanding how
things are gonna change and by putting
those into the same diagram in the same
picture you create an opportunity for
the technical team and the business team
to actually work together over time to
meet the needs of the market and and we
find that this technique which we call
market driven roadmaps where the
technical leader is in the room at the
same time with the product person
creating that vision of the future has
this tremendous effect of helping link
the two teams together and helping them
be productive together now the other
part that you talked about was this
notion of how do I deal with updates in
the field how do I deal with a service
in the field and notice that that's a
business decision that's affected by the
architectural choices exactly right so
the business team says you know Marcus
it's really important that we be able to
update the software when it has a bug
yeah and so as an architect you kind of
scratch your head and you say well okay
what do I need to do technically to
implement the business desire or a goal
of having it be updated in the field
whether then you would say well I have
two component eyes my system well that's
just good engineering but more
importantly I have to identify each
component in such a way that not the
system is versioned but each component
is versioned if I can say that you know
the bug is in this module version 2.2
and I'm going to go download this new
particular module version 2.3 and then
it creates a configuration
sophistication and then you have to do
your testing infrastructure where you're
testing the permeate
patience so it's again to me that
question is really it really gets to the
heart of what I care about which is the
business has a goal called make it easy
to update no and the technical team can
do that I mean we know how to do this we
know the techniques to do this but it's
intertwined with the business you know
where we have to go back to the business
people and say well what if I'm building
embedded software and you have to go to
the business people and say ok if you
want me to update the software in the
field then I need more money for the
hardware because I need room in the
hardware to continue the new update and
then you have to go figure out the new
economic model cuz now it's not you know
five dollars in material cost but seven
dollars in material costs you have to
figure out if you can make money or if
it's cheaper maybe not for the
environment but might be cheaper for
your business to not make it upgradable
and throw it out so is this where the
two terms market tech chure and
architecture come into play I mean but
most people know the term architecture I
guess and that has in most circuits like
has a bad connotation because it means
basically drawing power points in a way
that people like the pictures but that's
not what you're talking about I guess
not at all so in the book I introduced
two terms one is architecture and the
market act and the other is architecture
with a tee and the architect so most of
the time I think of the technical
architect is the Tarka Tecton and if you
think about what they're responsible for
you can kind of see the distinction of
the market decked and the target X so at
architect is responsible for the overall
architectural style is it a layered
system is it a pipeline is it a
blackboard is it a kernel architecture
if the market tech has the similar kind
of responsibility for how the market how
you go to market meaning how do you
charge customers how do you build them
how do you service them how do you
support them these are all choices that
the marketing team makes about how they
want to work with the market so as the
market echt the same as what some people
call the product manager yes in many
cases and in those cases the product
manager is the market okay and and I'll
point out that in our industry we've
learned that technical architects are
special people and they're rare
and good ones are rare yeah and we've
also learned that in product management
actually good product manager is a very
rare person there's many product
managers who are ex engineers who aren't
particularly skilled at it because they
want to design the system and then the
other problem with product managers is
they come with no technical background
of any kind right so I got an MBA in
finance and now I'm a product manager
half doesn't work it doesn't work
there's there is a need in our
particular industry to have some unique
skill and in fact that's one of the
things that my company is devoted to
trying to help understand which is
product management of software
technologies is different than product
management of coffee and coca-cola and
chairs they're different skills why is
that well the fundamental reason is
software is not sold it is licensed it
is intellectual property so when you
bought your chair you didn't have a
license agreement or when you bought a
pen yeah maybe it's going to be married
one day well but that's when the chair
gets smart and it knows how how to make
itself hard or soft based on whether
you're tired or not right because it has
sensors built in in some software person
right because software's really well
some software person wrote the software
to make the chair adjustable right now
like I'm holding a pen in our interview
and this pen was bought yeah it's I own
it right I physically own the second I
could sell it to you without
restrictions you cannot do that with
software and so one of the most
fundamental distinctions between
software as a product versus any other
kind of product is the notion of
intellectual property and licensing and
how the license terms both affect the
software affect the technical team and
affect how the market evolves but but
also I guess there is like more like
technical reasons why software is
different from from chairs because I
mean people always say that chairs and
many other things are governed by all
kinds of physical chemical and
biological laws absolutely which you
can't negotiate away in software at
least people think it's different well
in many ways it is and one of the things
that changes about software is that
because the hardware continues to
improve so rapidly we can actually do
things now in software that we couldn't
can see but mostly because of
algorithmic complexity and of course
just to make sure this is me not Luke
probably turn his phone off no but
you're right I mean the whole and and
and and I can't I can't disagree right
though the whole notion of physicality
of uh you know and for example the
software it's interesting software bits
don't degrade right they last forever
where chairs in physical objects degrade
no but the relevancy of the bits
degrades because of changing in the
environment and information has actually
saw the value of the software degrades
to it mechanically fades away but its
usefulness its usefulness yeah I mean
how many of us find you usefulness out
of das 3.1 anymore CPM or an old
operating I just recently found an
emulator for the Amstrad computers back
then with with all the games so I like
that useful yeah of course but um mmm
that's a good view I didn't didn't think
about that yet so that so software
actually ages in the same sense as
Harper products age just that it's not
physically deteriorating that's right
and so it confuses people like so
software people when we say that we
actually we're comfortable with it we go
yeah it makes sense
whereas non-technical people go I don't
understand it's not wearing out help me
understand yeah so one thing that I'd
like to talk about a little bit which is
bit beyond I think beyond what you
described at the book is product lines
how is product line development
different in that sense how is a product
that's part of a product line is there
different things we with regards to the
process and roadmap first half I am very
excited about the work on software
product lines I think it's some of the
best work that's ever come out of the
software engineering Institute I'm very
excited about it yeah I really and I
know that in other places around the
world product lines are becoming more
prominent I do think that there are some
differences about product lines because
product lines are fundamentally about an
architecture that was created with a
business
this in mind and that's that's different
than architectures that were created
with a indirect business purpose in mind
so for example we might talk about
scalable transaction processing
architectures and yes the business
purpose was scalability whereas in in a
product line architecture you're
typically analyzing the product line
relative to a set of market segments to
create that investment right up front so
I I think all of the normal practices
that a product manager does and many of
the practices that an architect does are
appropriate I think they get extended
and emphasized in a product line
architecture it somehow funny I've been
discussing this product line stuff with
with several people recently because
it's also for me it's very interesting
and maybe even we recorded this in one
of the previous podcasts on product I
don't know many way so we have once said
that when he looks at this product line
stuff most of this stuff is just
software engineering done right so it's
not necessarily specific to product
lines it's just that those practices and
best practices become even more
important if you do product lines
yeah and I've had that I've had that
point of view too because I've read the
the seminal book software product lines
and and I read it and I'm like well I've
done that I mean that's how I've done
systems in the past yeah I think the
difference is in the the expected output
of a software product line is that you
get multiple instantiations relative to
market segments and domains
whereas software engineering done right
is still typically done for one
particular instantiation or one
particular domain and yeah I think
that's a worthy distinct yeah of course
I mean there is this focus on on
extendibility and of the ability of
explicitly manage variations and and and
blah blah blah but but many of the
things that people talk about in product
lines would also be useful in non
product line invent right yeah and
notice that notice that what we're
really distinguishing is the input
versus the output right the input to the
well designed architecture is the same
as the input to the well design product
line I want to achieve this goal
it's the output that's different the
output of a well-designed single
architecture is just a single
architecture or single instantiation of
the system
the output of a software product line is
multiple instantiations of that system
in controlled ways with different price
performance or different structural
characteristics but the other thing you
know the other thing that I've been
finding is I've worked with companies
who are doing software product lines is
that people who have built
multi-platform software and people who
have built software that goes that is
highly internationalized tend to have an
advantage in thinking about product
lines because they're used to the notion
of I want to have this core that is
expressed in different platforms and I
want to have this core that's expressed
in different user segments or
populations now and so those people
naturally are employing the probably the
good practices of software engineering
there seem to be adapting product lines
faster yep so let's talk about some of
the aspects that are important to
consider when discussing about the
influences of business aspects on
software technology so let's take let's
take one of my favorites technology in
licensing it's virtually impossible to
build a product today on your own mm-hmm
you're you're building on an operating
system yeah I mean the embedded guys
sometimes can do it on their own but
even embedded teams will often use
embedded operating systems yeah well
again going back to this notion of
software isn't sole that's licensed
everything that you're building on has a
license that governs its terms of use
and so as an architect you're not only
making technical choices about the
performance of the component or its
functionality you have to start being
aware of the license agreement and you
have to say I I want to bring in this
component and by using this component I
get this advantage but I have to
understand the terms and conditions of
the use of that component and I'll give
you a concrete example some years ago we
were brought in to work with a client
who wanted to build software as a
service in ASP and they wanted to build
it on a particular vendors g2e container
well as it turns out the vendor license
for the j2ee container was different
when it was hosted versus when when it
was deployed on site and the
of the license for hosting was untenable
it was too expensive to host it using
their container license so we had to
pick a different container and in the
process yes theoretically theoretically
j2ee containers are completely portable
yeah they're not right now so then we
had to spend about two months of
development costs rewriting the whole
thing to get into the other to get to an
open source j2ee container that's the
kind of issue that technology licensing
can come into play and of course with
open source manok people who don't
understand open source licensing or the
issues of open source licensing can make
mistakes even they may not be trying to
make do the wrong thing but they may
make a mistake because they don't
understand the license terms and that's
something I mean I'm using quite a lot
of open source software I'm also
producing open source software in the
open architecture team and when we
became part of the Eclipse platform so
we moved from you know just another open
source project on SourceForge to
becoming part of the Eclipse platform or
the Eclipse project and we had to do
quite some I think the term is due
diligence finding out what what kind of
libraries we were using and making sure
that we don't use anything that is from
a licensing perspective unclear and we
didn't care about that before I mean you
know it's open source just use it yeah
just you care yeah absolutely we have to
and so and so that's a that's an
important consideration I think of any
architect they have to know these things
and what's interesting is that you might
say oh no no no Luke you know the
business team should know that well the
reality is is the business team can't
understand the meaning of the term so
they can walk up to you when they can
say hey this license says that I'm not
supposed to expose the API well what do
they know about exposing API and you as
a technical person say well what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna wrap the API yeah
well a lawyer who's smart and both would
say well wrapping an API is similar to
exposing it because you're not doing any
value-added work on top of it yeah so so
the technical people really do have a
responsibility to understand a little
bit about this next one without that we
like to talk about as
portability there's a portability is a
really funny thing right because a lot
of developers care about their skill and
writing portable code yeah I was about
to mention that yeah it's it's like I
know how to write portable code and it's
a rare skill and it's and let's add
another indirection layer so we can
exchange a database you know and and so
what I find is that portability is not a
good choice when developers think it's
cool or when early customers and the
early phases of a product growth say
well I've got different needs and I want
you to support them what what you really
want to do is then a product team you
want to evaluate the notion of
portability based on market share it's
it's economics how much does it take me
to write the portable code and does it
make sense for me to support that other
platform now what's interesting is that
I I explicitly said write that code and
hopefully your listeners are saying no
no it's more money than just writing the
code and it is you've got to have a few
a teams you got to have support teams
your sales team might have to have you
know you know let's say you're selling
enterprise software and you're selling
it on different platforms like a Mac
platform and a Windows platform and a
Solaris platform well does your sales
team have to be trained in all platforms
and what about the differences in
platforms etc etc so I I understand
portable systems development I have
managed teams doing portable development
I've created portable products more
often than that though I think that
portability is overrated yes I would
agree because especially for example on
the database side I mean if you're
developing real products that people can
deploy on their database and it's
different but typically also in like an
IT projects I mean your customer will
most likely never ever change the
database because it's too expensive and
if these typical you know lifelong
licenses with Oracle well it's not only
that it's too expensive so let's say
that you're a company that has a big
investment in Oracle mm-hm and it's not
the data that's the expense in any
system right it's the humans right so
it's not just the fact that you've got
this big licensing agreement
Oracle it said all your DBA s no Oracle
and they know the ins and outs of Oracle
and they're comfortable with Oracle not
that Oracle is perfect or it's terrible
it's just that they understand how to
make Oracle worth yeah so then you walk
up to them and say well I want you to
use this new thing because it's cheaper
and they're thinking but I've got to
retrain everything I've learned in my
career and what we often what I've often
seen is that when people make those
kinds of changes the people change yeah
they go fight in a job where they can
use all yes absolutely here because I
know Oracle yeah
yeah that's especially true for
databases there so I think we talked
already about a little bit about the
deployment stuff update ability and
things so do you want to add on that
well when I talk about deployment and
one of the things that I write about is
the notion of people put a big
distinction in the world right now
between is it hosted at the customer
site or is it hosted in a data center
and some people call those application
service providers in Silicon Valley the
cool term is software as a service you
know you run it like salesforce.com yeah
when you're when you're talking about
the the architecture of a product I
think in general the architecture of
deployment should be independent of the
architecture of the business
functionality meaning I shouldn't bake
in assumptions about how I've deployed
and yet people did that all the time I
mean what they found for example in the
early days of hosting software was that
they they the software was inadvertently
designed to be one customer on one
database oh yeah and then we had to
learn how to redesign database tables to
have what's called multi-tenancy yeah so
that's one issue right and so when you
really approach it from from a fresh
perspective what you want to say is I
have to expect in the modern world that
my software is going to be flexibly
deployed some customers aren't gonna
want to put it on site some customers
might want me to host it or I might want
a third party to host it and therefore
I'm gonna make choices in my
architecture so that they it can be
flexibly deployed and and again to your
comment earlier about well product line
architectures are just really
fundamentally good architecture
design I think deployment choices are
fundamentally good design choices now I
want to add one thing that I didn't
write about in the book that is an
important distinction there are
capabilities that you can create for
your customers when your software is
hosted that are different than when it's
deployed on-site I'll give you a
concrete example yeah let's say I'm
doing a a data acquisition system for
supermarket HVAC controls so I've got
supermarkets in in and I'm managing the
temperatures and and the thermometers
and the latest HDI C stands for air
conditioning so I've got the system that
does that now if I put the software at
my customers site they can look at
things like trends and they can
understand how the weather impacts their
energy usage but what they can't
determine is how their store is doing
relative to other stores from other
companies and when I host it I can
aggregate the data and then I can do
what's called syndication or syndicated
data analysis and I can get performance
statistics about how I'm doing relative
to other people mm-hm so what I try to
get the business team to first think
about before I talk to the architectures
is they say are there unique services or
information that you can provide to your
market when you host and if the answer
is yes I can get something unique well
then it's a little bit more compelling
to go hosting it as you're providing a
better business value yeah and you're
not making the choice based on
architecture because most good
architects once they understand that
hosting is a requirement or flexible
deployment as a requirement they say oh
well I'm going to design my system to be
multi-tenant and here's what I need to
do to be multi-tenant and you know then
you add the security of the database and
things like that but but the real point
is you gotta bring it first to the
business value what what am i offering
to the market that's different when I
hosted versus when I don't host it whisk
them off the crowd right that's right
that stuff yeah of course sometimes the
crowd is idiots so so you don't want to
do that yeah so um before we talk a
little bit about innovation and product
innovation
I'd like to touch briefly on on one
thing that I personally find quite
important and that is branding
I mean I've I haven't ever really done
product except maybe the podcast I mean
in some sense the podcast soft
engineering radio is a kind of product
what is right it is a product if you
know I'm wearing this t-shirt that does
some advertising I have you know so it's
a brand yeah you have a logo you have a
name if website you for you know way of
doing the episode so you're really
building a brand in some sense and so I
think you'll certainly have some
thoughts about that I do so so in the
book I talk about brand and brand
elements for software architectures
again this is one of those areas that
does distinguish a product from an IT
project yeah it doesn't have a lot of
need for branding but but it's really
funny because when you when you drill
into the details you find that brand
issues surface and many of funny ways
like for example if I'm installing
software on my laptop I usually put it
by convention in Windows in C program
files but now I have a question do I put
the name of the company as the directory
with the name of the product do I put
the name of the product do I put the
version of the product I'm installing
into the directory structure similarly
when I'm doing software let's say I'm
running software as a service and I put
my company's logo out there what if my
company is using it internally with
their users maybe they want to see their
logo and now I have to define what are
the standards of the graphic and how do
I upload it and how do I change it and
who can upload it and who can change it
so branding and brand elements are very
important things that that we need to
understand in products and the architect
needs to be in a have an awareness of it
so that they're using them properly and
making the right choices for change
ability and extensibility mm-hmm which
is kind of funny it's also important
whether you try to put your company name
in the foreground or your product name
that's for example on a in some cases
the company name is the same name as as
the product name Google Skype I mean
Google has other stuff done in search
engine but the search engine is Google
and so I think it's also important to
make this distinction whether you want
to make your company
entity or whether you really like
building a product which which hasn't
happened yet which how about calm this
is this is all the marketing aside of
things for example you know it gets
funny when companies acquire companies
so for example Symantec acquired Norton
AntiVirus well the Norton brand was so
strong that they've never thrown it away
and still refer to it as Norton
AntiVirus
even though technically its semantics
Norton AntiVirus yeah you know we we
call it and it's sometimes we say we
tend to say Microsoft Word but we tend
to say Excel we don't say Microsoft
Excel think about it when you think
about how people talk in the language
they choose yeah it's very interesting
to see when is it the company like you
said is the company product or is it
product mm-hmm-hmm cool yeah yeah yeah
mm-hmm okay so um let's look a little
bit about this whole business of
innovation and and to some extent also
requirements gathering I guess because
um as we said we talked about that a
little bit in the preparation of this
episode and and I think coming up with a
product idea is typically something very
creative there isn't much of a process
involved and then as you explained you
release like version one and you have a
couple of things on your backlog that
you wanted to be in 1.0 but it didn't
get in there because of time to market
considerations over to is also typically
simple you just add all the stuff you
always wanted to add but now what do you
do next how do you yeah how do you
communicate with your users or how do
you that's right
so so having been in several startups
they they typically have the same
structure as you outlined right some
some really creative person says oh if I
see this problem in this need and I'm
gonna write some software to go go fix
that problem and they may have be
solving their own problem or they may
have done some market research or some
testing or whatever to figure out that
it was worth doing but when you get into
release two when you get into release
three you start to say well what do I do
next
how do I keep my innovation pipeline
flowing you know and so what I found was
that um
being a good engineer I just would walk
up to my customers and say hey what do
you want and of course that doesn't work
so then I went to the field of usability
it doesn't work why well people don't
know what they want okay
the standard you know when you ask
someone what they want they don't really
know they kind of can tell you what they
don't like but they kind of can't tell
you what they like it's kind of like you
know when you're dating right it's easy
to see someone that you don't like but
it's not always hard to predict what you
do yeah where discriminators is humans
right the brain is designed to
discriminate so so then I moved into the
field of usability and I read all about
usability man and I learned about
prototyping I thought wow prototyping
that makes it better right because you
know through paper and pencil sketching
interfaces you can show them interfaces
and you can get rapid feedback and
there's lots of good work in that field
and it's very important to to do
prototyping but I found that prototyping
didn't actually help me understand the
motivating need of the customer it
helped me understand whether a customer
found my idea acceptable but it didn't
necessarily solve the problem yep so I
started playing around over about 10
years with different games and different
techniques and what I found was that
when you let people do activities you
can get much richer understanding of
what they're trying to accomplish and
the problems are facing so after about
10 years of doing this I wrote a book
called innovation games which was just
published and in innovation games I
described 12 ways to work with your
customers through activities or games
that give you insight into deep needs
and deep understanding of what they want
and that the goal of the book is to
provide readily accessible tools to
software people or technical people
because we're frankly not trained to
talk with customers right marketing
people they they're giving classes on
this engineers are given classes in you
know algorithmic complexity but not a
very good way to learn how to talk with
a customer right
so so that goal of the book is to
outline in very clear very simple steps
here's how you plan the event here's how
you bring customers in here's what you
do here's how you post process the
results and here's how you use them in
your product planning purposes and we
found that these games are very very
successful they've been used by lots and
lots of different companies they've
helped improve products mm-hmm
they've helped product strategy they've
even created new product lines and
product offerings at companies based on
the ideas and the innovations that occur
out of the game can you give us like two
or three examples of such games so we
got a absolutely
so one game is called buy a feature and
it's helped it's used to help understand
customers priorities of features so
let's take a premise that a development
team as a finite resource yes usually
usually so that means you don't have you
don't have the ability to do everything
you want
so what product managers typically do is
they go out and talk with customer one
and get what their needs are and they
get then they talk with customer two and
they get their needs and they keep this
pairwise conversation they get a bunch
of customer needs and then they sort
through it what buy a feature does is it
says let's bring all the customers into
the room
let's price the features and give them
play money hmm and the amount of money
that we give them isn't enough to buy
all the features because development is
a limited resource and let's watch who
negotiates with whom to buy what so
let's say there's six customers at the
table and I each gave them $10 and one
of the features is $40 and one features
$30 and one features $20 eventually
they're gonna start running out of money
and to get a feature they have to
collaborate mm-hm and what you're
watching is the developer in the room is
you're watching well who collaborates
with whom and you find that people will
collaborate to buy what they want and
the more that they collaborate the more
important that feature is to the market
but that of course only works if you can
identify your customers or at least a
subset if you have the typical X rink
wrapped stuff you can't obviously get
all your custom absolutely so
by a feature that's one game another
game is what would be give them a hot
tub so give them a hot tub is the use of
outrageous features to determine what is
called the product boundary so let's go
back to the product management and
technical architecture product
management is making choices about
what's in and out of the product
similarly the Technical Architect makes
choices about the product boundary they
say this is in my product or this is
something I'm gonna license in right
these are boundary questions so what
give them a hot tub does is it uses
outrageous features to determine what
features customers want and so what
happens is when you're presented with an
outrageous idea your brain needs to
protect itself so your brain will say
well that's just stupid
mm-hm well okay fine or the brain will
say I didn't even hear it
like I ignored the stimulus in the
environment because it's too weird
okay but the magic occurs when we give
you an outrageous feature and then your
brain says I've got to make sense of it
because I've got to resolve cognitive
dissonance so at outrageous idea induces
cognitive dissonance and so your brain
transforms it into something that makes
sense and it's that transformation
process that gives you insight into the
kind of the features that your customers
really want so what you're saying is
you're proposing nonsense and the
customers yeah you know that's nonsense
but what I really need is like this in
that exactly correct and it sounds like
it doesn't work but it actually works
very well and there's a lot of
psychological research that talks about
how we respond to stimulus that is
nonsense and sometimes we ignore it we
just say oh it's nonsense and you move
on but sometimes we do exactly what you
did you say well it's really kind of
nonsense but you know what I really
would this would make sense to me and it
would make sense to me but something
that creates interesting and empower and
excitement another game is actually
based on the field of ethnographic
observation and ethnographic observation
is going out in the field and working
with customers
and it's we call it The Apprentice not
unlike the TV show but if many software
people have a term called dogfooding
and your own dog food eat your own dog
out so eat your own dog food is using
your own software yeah the problem is
that most software teams can't really
use their own software because they're
not the people using the work that's why
I always say that you that you can't
necessarily adopt the practices of the
people who develop Eclipse they're
always considered as are this a great
team they built this wonderful stable
scalable platform and they do dog
footing all the time
but you can of course only do this if
you develop development tools that's
right so it's a great idea but it falls
apart yeah so what we do with the same
concept is we we actually put developers
at our customers site and we have them
use the software with the customer as a
guide so you can't dog food like for
example if you're a software developer
working on retail cash registers like
you're working on software that makes
the cash register run chances are your
software developer you're not a cashier
at a store yeah but what we will do with
customers is we'll actually put the
developer at a store that has their cash
register and we'll have them be a cash
register operator for say an hour or two
and then the cash register expert will
say we'll see this is how it works and
by having that feeling of how it's
really working or not working gives the
developer first empathy all right it
creates empathy for the customer empathy
for the experience and it helps them
understand Wow when I'm building
software this is the kind of person that
cares about it and this is what they
have to do to do their job and it also
really helps to understand the domain
I've once been working for a company who
builds these huge container terminals in
Hamburg home and of course since I'm an
engineer I of course liked you know to
see these big things so the plan was to
actually go there go on top of such a
crane and really look at what's
happening and how these container
transport things you know drive around
and how this all works to get a better
understanding of what the domain is for
which we're trying to build this you
know this like state machine that
controls the crane order right because
the state machine that controls a crane
is very abstract exactly and and there's
no emotion then there's no yes exactly
and engineers do much better when they
have that personal connection as to what
customers are doing yeah especially if
it's in some sense cool yeah oh yeah oh
yeah has it's everything has a sense of
coolness yeah banking for me it doesn't
banking doesn't or bankers it does okay
so um but although you you you you talk
about this stuff in the context of
innovation and product development it
could also be considered as a way of
doing requirements engineering
oh absolutely engineering let's let's
take a step back so so so the innovation
games are technically a form of market
research and it's called qualitative
market research and what my what I
believe is that requirements gathering
is just another form of market research
and because I define market research is
any activity that you undertake to
better understand your customer so if
you're undertaking an activity that is
working with people or trying to
understand them better to me that's a
form of market research well that's what
requirements gathering is how do I
understand your needs to create better
software well you know requirements
gathering and the whole field of
requirements gathering there's many
wonderful techniques that work
unfortunately some of them are pretty
dry and fun yeah the the real point
about the other point about innovation
games is that there's an element of fun
to all of the games and many of the
games result in in people generating
pictures and artwork that you can take
back to the rest of the team and share
with them and say look this is what a
customer said yeah and this is this is
what they meant when they said it and
instead of seeing you know some very
boring you know 12-point times Roman
font in a Word document they can
actually see customer handwriting and
they can see a customer generating
exactly what they were looking for yeah
and I really think it's critical that
you involve groups of people so you have
this element of discussion because if
you just go to a customer and say hey
tell me what you want sketch it then
they either won't be able to do it or
they will sketch the bathtub right
that's really stupid stuff that are
either
unrealistic of which they think they
need but they don't need it I have to
have interactivity where people talk to
each other and kind of negotiate the
future and you know it's fun about this
is that is that it actually doesn't have
to be a big deal meaning many companies
have natural opportunities to talk with
customers they have user groups they
have annual conferences and what's funny
about this is that and I'm going to talk
about this in my keynote later today at
the but the the only thing that's
holding back developers from attending
those events is they don't often ask me
if there's a user group meeting and
you're a developer say hey could I go to
the user group meeting and and just
start hanging out with customers and
talk with them and then there's some
guidelines as a developer right you
shouldn't make promises because it's
your job and you shouldn't you know say
things are bad or good you know don't
commiserate you know don't say oh I'm
gonna fix that bug for you because I may
not fix that bug yeah so once you learn
a couple of light guidelines of how to
talk you can participate in those events
and get access to it but you kind of got
to ask that question yeah cuz they're
not gonna come ask you and they're not
gonna go you know they're not gonna the
marketing team isn't gonna go over an
engineering and say hey engineers come
on out to the user event but they would
love to have you there and and users
would probably be happy if they were
able to talk to like real experts and
not you know just marketing people
that's right they so it's entirely
acceptable when a customer walks up to
you and says could you tell me a little
bit more about why it works this way and
then you can say well here's what we
were thinking and here's how and the
customer was oh okay that makes sense to
me it's very non-threatening yeah I
think that's more or less all I had in
mind do you want to like you add any SSA
and as I copied from other podcast any
pearls of wisdom that you want to leave
any pearls of wisdom I would simply
summarize the way we started which is
business and technology are intertwined
they're not distinct and the choices
that technical people make influence the
business and the choices that the
business makes influence the technical
people and understanding that
interaction creates better products and
better architectures okay so thanks Luke
for being on the show
I'll let you know once we posted it
thank you very much
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se
- radio net although we prefer entries
in our comment system on the website so
other people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details